"Are There Health Benefits of
Spending Time in Nature?"
For perhaps 99.99% of our
time on Earth as a species,
we’ve been living outdoors
in the natural environment.
Might there be a health benefit
to returning now and again,
and surrounding ourselves with nature?
That’s a question urban
planners have asked:
Are people living in
greener areas healthier
than people living in less green areas?
Should we put in a park
or another carpark?
In a greener environment people
report fewer symptoms of illness
and have better perceived
general and mental health,
and by a considerable amount.
Assuming the link is cause and effect,
10% more greenspace leads to
a decrease in the number of
symptoms that is comparable
with a decrease in age by five years,
but that is a big assumption.
Still, you could imagine some potential
mechanisms of why it could be.
It could mean less air pollution.
And air pollution is no joke;
it's the fifth leading cause of death
on Planet Earth, wiping out
about five million people a year.
Though, of course, our diet kills twice
as many, as killer risk factor #1.
So, it could be an antipollution effect.
Or maybe there’s something special
about experiencing greenspaces
beyond them just offering
more opportunities to exercise,
but that’s probably
the simplest explanation:
natural settings simply
promote “health-enhancing behavior
rather than having specific
and direct benefits for health.”
It’s harder to go jogging in
the park when there is no park.
Ironically, it seems that even
when people have access to nature,
they don’t necessarily
take advantage of it.
And, even if there was a link,
instead of natural environments
drawing out increased physical activity,
maybe physically active individuals
are just drawn to living
where there’s nature.
But what I wanted to know is, apart
from the promotion of physical activity,
are there added benefits to health of
mere exposure to natural environments?
Now certainly, just exposure to
sunlight can treat things like
seasonal aﬀective disorder and
provide the sunshine vitamin—vitamin D.
But are there any other inherent benefits?
You don’t know, until you put it to the test.
Some of the studies are just silly, though.
At first, I thought this was
about academic achievement
and vegetarianism,
but no—vegetation.
They found a correlation
between non-forest vegetation
and graduation rates for schools.
Maybe the ivy league edge
is all just ‘cause of the ivy...
OK, but this study starts to
make things more interesting.
The view through a window may
influence recovery from surgery.
At this suburban hospital,
some patient rooms looked out at trees,
and others just to a brick wall.
And, the “surgical patients assigned
to rooms with windows looking out
on a natural scene had shorter
postoperative hospital stays”
and took fewer potent
painkillers than similar patients
in similar rooms but with
windows facing a brick wall.
You can’t chalk that
up to a vitamin D effect.
What could it be about
just looking at trees?
Maybe it’s the vitamin G,
just the color of green.
We know how healthy
it is to eat our greens.
What about just looking at them?
Researchers had people
exercise while watching a video
simulating going through a
natural-color green setting,
the same video in black and white,
or everything flipped to red, and…
no differences were noted
with the exception of the red
just making people feel angry.
The most interesting suggested
mechanism I ran across was fractals.
You know how all the
branches of a tree kind of have
the same shape of a tree themselves?
Fractal patterns are found throughout
nature, where you can see a cascade
of self-similar patterns
over a range of magniﬁcations.
And hook people up to an
EEG, and for some reason
our brain apparently seems to like them.
Regardless of the mechanism,
if you compile together all the
controlled studies on using nature
as a health promotion intervention,
you tend to see mostly psychological
benefits, whereas the findings
related to physical outcomes
were less consistent.
The most common type
of study outcome was
self-reported measures of
different emotions.
Like, what makes you feel better,
staring at a kiwifruit orchard,
or staring at a building?
Awkwardly described, thanks
presumably to the language barrier,
as a comparison of
“synthetic versus organic stimulation.”
Natural settings may make
people more attentive, less sad,
but when it comes to
some objective measures
like blood pressure,
no significant effect.
So, you know you ask people who
exercise outdoors and they say
they feel great, suggesting
that “green exercise”
activities have the capacity to
increase mood, focus, and energy
and within just like five minutes
of being out there in the woods.
Yet these studies tended
not to be randomized trials.
They just asked people who
already sought out nature
what they thought about nature;
and so, no wonder they like it—
otherwise they wouldn’t be out there.
But hey, nature-based interventions
are low cost, often free in fact,
and non-invasive unless
you count the mosquitoes.
So, if you want “a natural high”,
I say go for it, whatever makes you happy.
Though evidently not all
green exercisers like trees.
Golfers just viewed them as obstacles.